<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Life | Thinking in Crowd / 鹄思乱想]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.thinkingincrowd.me/blog/categories/life/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.thinkingincrowd.me/"/>
  <updated>2013-11-25T08:52:15+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.thinkingincrowd.me/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[鹄思乱想]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Short trip with Mom and Dad for Mother's Day]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.thinkingincrowd.me/blog/2006/05/18/short-trip-with-mom-and-dad-for-mothers-day/"/>
    <updated>2006-05-18T23:12:12+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.thinkingincrowd.me/blog/2006/05/18/short-trip-with-mom-and-dad-for-mothers-day</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>During this mother&rsquo;s day, Winnie &amp; I had a great vacation with my mom and dad.</p>

<p> </p>

<p><strong>1st Destination:</strong></p>

<p>We had a one day Macau tour on May 12th.  This was the first tour for my family.  When I was still in school, we have never go somewhere.  What is more, my dad prefers watching TV than going out.  He can lay on the sofa all day without moving! <img src="http://spaces.msn.com/rte/emoticons/smile_confused.gif" alt="" />  If this trip hasn&rsquo;t been planned to go gambling in Casino Lisboa in Macau.  I guess he would probably not coming to ZH.</p>

<p> </p>

<p>Anyway, We arrived at Macau around 11AM.  My mom didn&rsquo;t feel very well because of bus-sick and Vomiting serveral times.  (FYI.  It tooks about 3 hours from Huizhou to Zhuhai;  It tooks about 1 hour from where I live to the Customs between Zhuhai and Macau).  We quickly find a place for lunch first so that my mom can have a rest.  After lunch (noodle &amp; pork bread), we went sight-seeing around Avenida de Almeida Ribeiro (亞美打利庇？大馬路), Senado Square (議事亭前地), Rua de S. Paulo(大三巴街), Fortaleza do Monte Monte Fortress(大炮台).</p>

<p> </p>

<p>About 4:30PM, we decided to go to the Casino Lisboa.  I think my dad has already waited such a long time for this moment came.  Before entering the casino, we made a decision that we have to enter the casino through back door in order to win.<img src="http://spaces.msn.com/rte/emoticons/smile_tongue.gif" alt="" />  I have exchanged 4 chips (100MOP each) to play &ldquo;big &amp; small&rdquo;.  2 chips for my dad, 1 for my mom and 1 for winnie.</p>

<p> </p>

<p>Why none for me?  Because I always believe that I have no this kind of luck for gambling.  You don&rsquo;t believe?  Let me tell you this.  For the first round, we all had no idea what to bet and then winnie decided to took the first step for us.  She asked me, &ldquo;what do you bet?  Big or small?&rdquo;.  I thought for a while and said, &ldquo;Big."  Then winnie said loudly, "OK, I bet small&rdquo; and put 1 chip at the side for small.  I was stun by her.  &ldquo;Ding, ding, ding&rdquo;, desk clear and nobody was allowed to change anymore.  &ldquo;Small!!"  Can you feel what my feeling at that time?<img src="http://spaces.msn.com/rte/emoticons/smile_confused.gif" alt="" />  To be angry, or to be happy?  haha, both.</p>

<p> </p>

<p>After that, my mom and dad became active and discussed with winnie about what should bet next.  Another unbelievable thing is when I asked my dad to take a shot and try, but he said no, it&rsquo;s better to let your mom gamble, she&rsquo;s more lucky than me.  Can you believe it?  I can&rsquo;t!  The one who want to gamble most doesn&rsquo;t gamble after he&rsquo;s there.<img src="http://spaces.msn.com/rte/emoticons/smile_tongue.gif" alt="" /></p>

<p> </p>

<p>At the end, we counted the chips and found that winnie won 350MOP, my mom won 100MOP, and my dad won 200MOP.  Haha, we won a free trip to Macau.</p>

<p> </p>

<p><strong>2nd Destination:</strong></p>

<p>After a busy day in Macau, we felt very tired and slept until 9AM on the next morning.  The next day&rsquo;s destination is the imperial-hotspring in order to take a rest.   But it&rsquo;s about 2 hours car from my dorm.  It would more than 3 hours if we take the bus.</p>

<p> </p>

<p>We decided to go to Wanzi to have a seafood lunch and shop for dried seafood first.  You have to respect my mom&rsquo;s bargain ability.  We only use 350RMB to buy several bags of those stuffs.  Besides, I still have to thank Cindy to introduce her familiar supplier to me so that we can get lower price.</p>

<p> </p>

<p>After buying the dried seafood, we bought the fresh seafood for our lunch.  This time, the seafood is not as cheap as before, maybe near the Fishing moratorium duration.  But we tried something new, the Sea urchins.  You can take a look at the picture of its shell after I have done with it.<img src="http://spaces.msn.com/rte/emoticons/smile_tongue.gif" alt="" /></p>

<p> </p>

<p>We arrived the hotspring after lunch.  Nothing special.  Just one word:&ldquo;Relax&rdquo;.</p>

<p> </p>

<p>Ending:</p>

<p>I lost about 2000RMB during this trip.  But for 4 people, it&rsquo;s not expensive indeed.  What is more, it&rsquo;s quite worthy because I can have such a great time with my parent.  I will make more money and go to other places with them!!  Yeah!.</p>

<p> </p>

<p>After words &ndash; A strange phenomenon: my mom didn&rsquo;t feel bus-sick and vomit anymore after winning in Casino.  haha<img src="http://spaces.msn.com/rte/emoticons/smile_teeth.gif" alt="" /></p>

<p> </p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[小茹语录(Keep updating)]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.thinkingincrowd.me/blog/2006/05/18/classic-statement-from-winnie-keep-updating/"/>
    <updated>2006-05-18T19:18:28+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.thinkingincrowd.me/blog/2006/05/18/classic-statement-from-winnie-keep-updating</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>以下是小茹经典的语录。都不明她的语言点解可以甘搞笑。<img src="http://spaces.msn.com/rte/emoticons/smile_teeth.gif" alt="" /></strong></p>

<p> </p>

<p><em>回气荡肠</em></p>

<p>  －意思：荡气回肠</p>

<p>  －情景：一晚，茹因吃得太饱，肚子发出“咕”一声。然后她就笑笑口甘爆出呢个词。</p>

<p> </p>

<p><em>双按</em></p>

<p>  －意思：双击、double click</p>

<p>  －情景：一晚准备放工，她要关UltraEdit的一个Tag，发现关不了，就话：“点解双按关唔到嘎？”。</p>

<p> </p>

<p><em>人地有压力嘎</em></p>

<p>  －情景：一晚，茹搽完药膏，大叫：“个盖呢？”。我就话：“是不是不在厅啊？”。茹答：“是啊。”后来她回到房，发现原来个盖系房。我就笑啦，点知她就爆出呢句。因为刚看完“巴士阿叔”，所以狂笑。</p>

<p> </p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[BangKok Trip]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.thinkingincrowd.me/blog/2006/03/29/bangkok-trip/"/>
    <updated>2006-03-29T00:09:59+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.thinkingincrowd.me/blog/2006/03/29/bangkok-trip</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>At 2:30PM on Mar 24, 2006, I was in the <img src="http://spaces.msn.com/rte/emoticons/airplane.gif" alt="" /> from Macau to BangKok.  I was going to have a three-days' trip in BangKok with some colleagues.  This was a company event rewarding the staffs worked for one year.</p>

<p> </p>

<p>This is not the first time I took <img src="http://spaces.msn.com/rte/emoticons/airplane.gif" alt="" />, but the first time I crossed my country&rsquo;s boundary.  At the end of the three-hours' <img src="http://spaces.msn.com/rte/emoticons/airplane.gif" alt="" />, our <img src="http://spaces.msn.com/rte/emoticons/airplane.gif" alt="" /> kept cycling in the sky for five times.  Maybe the airport had no place to let it land on at that time, but it was really a signal indicating an unforgetable trip.</p>

<p> </p>

<p>We finally had our dinner at 7:00PM that night.  We all were like starving wolfs.  Although the Thai food was a little spicy, it was very delicious.  Especially the fruit, the pineapple, watermelon, were as sweet as sugar.  Our table had had 3 dishes.<img src="http://spaces.msn.com/rte/emoticons/smile_shades.gif" alt="" />  We had tried our best to tasted and finished all the courses.  However, there were too many dishes to eat them all.</p>

<p> </p>

<p>The hotel is really wonderful.  This was the first time I stayed in five-star hotel.  The room is clean, comfortable and has necessary facilities.  However, it has one strange design that the bath room and the main room is separated by glass and shutter.  That means people outside the bath room can see the inside of the bathroom!  I still can&rsquo;t understand it.</p>

<p> </p>

<p>The meals, activities during this trip were great, especially the breakfast in the hotel and the night show (SIAM NIRAMIT).  The night show is Thai&rsquo;s traditional dancing.  We watched it in a beautiful decorated hall.  The lights, scenes, dancing were fantastic.  It is much much better than the Renyao show.</p>

<p> </p>

<p>Another unforgettable thing is the Thai Massage we had.  Before being massaged by the Massage people, I was very afraid to die in the joints twisting.  However, I really wanted to had it another time after massage.  Although it&rsquo;s a little ached during their pressing and twisting, the massage people really got to the points where your muscle and joints are tight.  You will feel kind of released and light after massage.  I just think it would be great if I can have Thai massage while I am working.  <img src="http://spaces.msn.com/rte/emoticons/smile_tongue.gif" alt="" /></p>

<p> </p>

<p>The last unbelievable and unforgettable thing is how crazy the HK colleagues can be.  At the second night in the hotel, I was invited to have a drink with some HK colleagues.  Playing games and drinking wine, we gradually became a little drunk and crazy.  We drank, tried every means to wake up other colleagues and wandered in hotel.  I can&rsquo;t believe how I could do that but I actually did it.  <strong><em>When play, play crazily; when work, work hard.</em></strong>  I can finally feel that after that night.  When will another crazy night come?  <img src="http://spaces.msn.com/rte/emoticons/smile_teeth.gif" alt="" /></p>

<p> </p>

<p>There were two small add-ons at the end of this trip.  One is that I left my worn clothes in the travel bus and realized this in the plane back to Macau from BangKok!<img src="http://spaces.msn.com/rte/emoticons/smile_confused.gif" alt="" />  Luckily the HK colleagues found it and bring them back to me.<img src="http://spaces.msn.com/rte/emoticons/smile_embaressed.gif" alt="" />  The other one is that it&rsquo;s required to pay extra money if we use the luggage case in taxi.  We knew that after being cheated by one taxi driver in Macau.<img src="http://spaces.msn.com/rte/emoticons/smile_angry.gif" alt="" />  We in fact didn&rsquo;t have much luggage and didn&rsquo;t need to put them there.</p>

<p> </p>

<p>This BangKok is also a UAT &ndash; unforgettable, adorable and treasurable.  I am looking forward for another one next year.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My 小黑]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.thinkingincrowd.me/blog/2006/03/28/my-t43/"/>
    <updated>2006-03-28T22:39:12+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.thinkingincrowd.me/blog/2006/03/28/my-t43</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I finally had my laptop.  It costs all my procession earned during these two years, but it&rsquo;s still worth the lost of money.</p>

<p>For someone that doesn&rsquo;t know what is 小黑, let me brief here.  小黑 is IBM Thinkpad.  My 小黑 is IBM T43 2668 BH4.</p>

<p>When I opened the case, I was shocked by the compactly arranged 小黑 and its accessories.  Although my 小黑 is black and has no fancy appearance, that is the style I love.  It&rsquo;s black, compact and professional.  It&rsquo;s like a professional dressed in a smart black suit with insight vision and in depth knowledge.</p>

<p>小黑, my dream.  It came true and it will come true.</p>

<p><a href="http://blufiles.storage.live.com/y1m11_8HmfikYjDWqaj_gDvvexnmwLefe_R0vV5vUSMzvqO3eZcPsJA-cxMCX_yqmWHbkvx-uleTPLU3E-plsHu07Zc8o9-HQCRFz4aDgl_5AJ_vI_Wbhgn2iDhpJwLwH2CUPjUOpUU-tY"><img src="http://blufiles.storage.live.com/y1m11_8HmfikYjDWqaj_gDvvexnmwLefe_R0vV5vUSMzvqO3eZcPsJA-cxMCX_yqmWHbkvx-uleTPLU3E-plsHu0ywUCiYUX_EcqZ_8hDpoZlIo5iiJQ8UyfNBeJztkIQ1tDqUzgda6bRk" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://blufiles.storage.live.com/y1mvNAS6Iw_gkeNZGC-mBLw16p3ekT4OS95zpm3tXYDswl3GaHzCpXzwiFVyu-F4onyRGdmbmk6Lkr8eZu4gIjiGadAQD_6hIL64OmgxChrslOlLWt94UOQq8RS1S3v34WJDfjG__Nnk88"><img src="http://blufiles.storage.live.com/y1mvNAS6Iw_gkeNZGC-mBLw16p3ekT4OS95zpm3tXYDswl3GaHzCpXzwiFVyu-F4onyRGdmbmk6Lkr8eZu4gIjiGVT0x9JWyGsXoFiYQ4q9yWryGNQFJ17N5t5AR-4hIh22bmNF9Rqd5Fg" alt="" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Many things happened.  All "unhappy".]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.thinkingincrowd.me/blog/2005/11/14/many-things-happened-all-unhappy/"/>
    <updated>2005-11-14T23:04:59+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.thinkingincrowd.me/blog/2005/11/14/many-things-happened-all-unhappy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In this shortly two months, many unhappy things happened around me.  Actually, I can&rsquo;t say those are all unhappy.  They just made me worried and greatly drew my attention.</p>

<p> </p>

<p>In fact, these &ldquo;unhappy&rdquo; things were all about the healthy condition of the ones I love and myself.  Suddenly, I realize that health is very important, but because of many kinds of reasons (endeavor to work, neglect, unwareness, etc.), its prominent role slips down to almost the most trivial one.  I think this was just the time it showed its anger and irritation.  <img src="http://spaces.msn.com/rte/emoticons/smile_tongue.gif" alt="" /></p>

<p> </p>

<p>Bear its announcement in mind, I will pay attention to my health and remind my friends &amp; relatives more.  It&rsquo;s always easier to cure an disease at the most earliest stage.</p>

<p> </p>

<p>In point of fact, it&rsquo;s quite lucky that these &ldquo;unhappy&rdquo; things happened.  Some diseases are discovered at the first stage before it get worse;  those made me alert to the importance of the body condition and more mature.  <img src="http://spaces.msn.com/rte/emoticons/smile_wink.gif" alt="" /></p>

<p> </p>

<p> </p>

<p>Wish everybody healthy and happy.  <img src="http://spaces.msn.com/rte/emoticons/smile_party.gif" alt="" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
