<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Tag: Trip | Thinking in Crowd / 鹄思乱想]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.thinkingincrowd.me/tags/trip/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.thinkingincrowd.me/"/>
  <updated>2013-04-13T13:10:28+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.thinkingincrowd.me/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[鹄思乱想]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Short trip with Mom and Dad for Mother's Day]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.thinkingincrowd.me/blog/2006/05/18/short-trip-with-mom-and-dad-for-mothers-day/"/>
    <updated>2006-05-18T23:12:12+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.thinkingincrowd.me/blog/2006/05/18/short-trip-with-mom-and-dad-for-mothers-day</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>During this mother's day, Winnie &amp; I had a great vacation with my mom and dad.</p>

<p> </p>

<p><strong>1st Destination:</strong></p>

<p>We had a one day Macau tour on May 12th.  This was the first tour for my family.  When I was still in school, we have never go somewhere.  What is more, my dad prefers watching TV than going out.  He can lay on the sofa all day without moving! <img src="http://spaces.msn.com/rte/emoticons/smile_confused.gif" alt="" />  If this trip hasn't been planned to go gambling in Casino Lisboa in Macau.  I guess he would probably not coming to ZH.</p>

<p> </p>

<p>Anyway, We arrived at Macau around 11AM.  My mom didn't feel very well because of bus-sick and Vomiting serveral times.  (FYI.  It tooks about 3 hours from Huizhou to Zhuhai;  It tooks about 1 hour from where I live to the Customs between Zhuhai and Macau).  We quickly find a place for lunch first so that my mom can have a rest.  After lunch (noodle &amp; pork bread), we went sight-seeing around Avenida de Almeida Ribeiro (亞美打利庇？大馬路), Senado Square (議事亭前地), Rua de S. Paulo(大三巴街), Fortaleza do Monte Monte Fortress(大炮台).</p>

<p> </p>

<p>About 4:30PM, we decided to go to the Casino Lisboa.  I think my dad has already waited such a long time for this moment came.  Before entering the casino, we made a decision that we have to enter the casino through back door in order to win.<img src="http://spaces.msn.com/rte/emoticons/smile_tongue.gif" alt="" />  I have exchanged 4 chips (100MOP each) to play "big &amp; small".  2 chips for my dad, 1 for my mom and 1 for winnie.</p>

<p> </p>

<p>Why none for me?  Because I always believe that I have no this kind of luck for gambling.  You don't believe?  Let me tell you this.  For the first round, we all had no idea what to bet and then winnie decided to took the first step for us.  She asked me, "what do you bet?  Big or small?".  I thought for a while and said, "Big."  Then winnie said loudly, "OK, I bet small" and put 1 chip at the side for small.  I was stun by her.  "Ding, ding, ding", desk clear and nobody was allowed to change anymore.  "Small!!"  Can you feel what my feeling at that time?<img src="http://spaces.msn.com/rte/emoticons/smile_confused.gif" alt="" />  To be angry, or to be happy?  haha, both.</p>

<p> </p>

<p>After that, my mom and dad became active and discussed with winnie about what should bet next.  Another unbelievable thing is when I asked my dad to take a shot and try, but he said no, it's better to let your mom gamble, she's more lucky than me.  Can you believe it?  I can't!  The one who want to gamble most doesn't gamble after he's there.<img src="http://spaces.msn.com/rte/emoticons/smile_tongue.gif" alt="" /></p>

<p> </p>

<p>At the end, we counted the chips and found that winnie won 350MOP, my mom won 100MOP, and my dad won 200MOP.  Haha, we won a free trip to Macau.</p>

<p> </p>

<p><strong>2nd Destination:</strong></p>

<p>After a busy day in Macau, we felt very tired and slept until 9AM on the next morning.  The next day's destination is the imperial-hotspring in order to take a rest.   But it's about 2 hours car from my dorm.  It would more than 3 hours if we take the bus.</p>

<p> </p>

<p>We decided to go to Wanzi to have a seafood lunch and shop for dried seafood first.  You have to respect my mom's bargain ability.  We only use 350RMB to buy several bags of those stuffs.  Besides, I still have to thank Cindy to introduce her familiar supplier to me so that we can get lower price.</p>

<p> </p>

<p>After buying the dried seafood, we bought the fresh seafood for our lunch.  This time, the seafood is not as cheap as before, maybe near the Fishing moratorium duration.  But we tried something new, the Sea urchins.  You can take a look at the picture of its shell after I have done with it.<img src="http://spaces.msn.com/rte/emoticons/smile_tongue.gif" alt="" /></p>

<p> </p>

<p>We arrived the hotspring after lunch.  Nothing special.  Just one word:"Relax".</p>

<p> </p>

<p>Ending:</p>

<p>I lost about 2000RMB during this trip.  But for 4 people, it's not expensive indeed.  What is more, it's quite worthy because I can have such a great time with my parent.  I will make more money and go to other places with them!!  Yeah!.</p>

<p> </p>

<p>After words - A strange phenomenon: my mom didn't feel bus-sick and vomit anymore after winning in Casino.  haha<img src="http://spaces.msn.com/rte/emoticons/smile_teeth.gif" alt="" /></p>

<p> </p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[BangKok Trip]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.thinkingincrowd.me/blog/2006/03/29/bangkok-trip/"/>
    <updated>2006-03-29T00:09:59+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.thinkingincrowd.me/blog/2006/03/29/bangkok-trip</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>At 2:30PM on Mar 24, 2006, I was in the <img src="http://spaces.msn.com/rte/emoticons/airplane.gif" alt="" /> from Macau to BangKok.  I was going to have a three-days' trip in BangKok with some colleagues.  This was a company event rewarding the staffs worked for one year.</p>

<p> </p>

<p>This is not the first time I took <img src="http://spaces.msn.com/rte/emoticons/airplane.gif" alt="" />, but the first time I crossed my country's boundary.  At the end of the three-hours' <img src="http://spaces.msn.com/rte/emoticons/airplane.gif" alt="" />, our <img src="http://spaces.msn.com/rte/emoticons/airplane.gif" alt="" /> kept cycling in the sky for five times.  Maybe the airport had no place to let it land on at that time, but it was really a signal indicating an unforgetable trip.</p>

<p> </p>

<p>We finally had our dinner at 7:00PM that night.  We all were like starving wolfs.  Although the Thai food was a little spicy, it was very delicious.  Especially the fruit, the pineapple, watermelon, were as sweet as sugar.  Our table had had 3 dishes.<img src="http://spaces.msn.com/rte/emoticons/smile_shades.gif" alt="" />  We had tried our best to tasted and finished all the courses.  However, there were too many dishes to eat them all.</p>

<p> </p>

<p>The hotel is really wonderful.  This was the first time I stayed in five-star hotel.  The room is clean, comfortable and has necessary facilities.  However, it has one strange design that the bath room and the main room is separated by glass and shutter.  That means people outside the bath room can see the inside of the bathroom!  I still can't understand it.</p>

<p> </p>

<p>The meals, activities during this trip were great, especially the breakfast in the hotel and the night show (SIAM NIRAMIT).  The night show is Thai's traditional dancing.  We watched it in a beautiful decorated hall.  The lights, scenes, dancing were fantastic.  It is much much better than the Renyao show.</p>

<p> </p>

<p>Another unforgettable thing is the Thai Massage we had.  Before being massaged by the Massage people, I was very afraid to die in the joints twisting.  However, I really wanted to had it another time after massage.  Although it's a little ached during their pressing and twisting, the massage people really got to the points where your muscle and joints are tight.  You will feel kind of released and light after massage.  I just think it would be great if I can have Thai massage while I am working.  <img src="http://spaces.msn.com/rte/emoticons/smile_tongue.gif" alt="" /></p>

<p> </p>

<p>The last unbelievable and unforgettable thing is how crazy the HK colleagues can be.  At the second night in the hotel, I was invited to have a drink with some HK colleagues.  Playing games and drinking wine, we gradually became a little drunk and crazy.  We drank, tried every means to wake up other colleagues and wandered in hotel.  I can't believe how I could do that but I actually did it.  <strong><em>When play, play crazily; when work, work hard.</em></strong>  I can finally feel that after that night.  When will another crazy night come?  <img src="http://spaces.msn.com/rte/emoticons/smile_teeth.gif" alt="" /></p>

<p> </p>

<p>There were two small add-ons at the end of this trip.  One is that I left my worn clothes in the travel bus and realized this in the plane back to Macau from BangKok!<img src="http://spaces.msn.com/rte/emoticons/smile_confused.gif" alt="" />  Luckily the HK colleagues found it and bring them back to me.<img src="http://spaces.msn.com/rte/emoticons/smile_embaressed.gif" alt="" />  The other one is that it's required to pay extra money if we use the luggage case in taxi.  We knew that after being cheated by one taxi driver in Macau.<img src="http://spaces.msn.com/rte/emoticons/smile_angry.gif" alt="" />  We in fact didn't have much luggage and didn't need to put them there.</p>

<p> </p>

<p>This BangKok is also a UAT - unforgettable, adorable and treasurable.  I am looking forward for another one next year.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Travel to Da Jiao Wan (大角湾) in Yang Jiang]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.thinkingincrowd.me/blog/2005/10/12/travel-to-da-jiao-wan-in-yang-jiang/"/>
    <updated>2005-10-12T19:39:47+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.thinkingincrowd.me/blog/2005/10/12/travel-to-da-jiao-wan-in-yang-jiang</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>On Sep 23rd, 2005 morning 8:00 AM, I was in the bus way to Yang Chun with Winnie's family, indicating the beginning of the travel to Da Jiao Wan.</p>

<p> </p>

<p>This travel is the first long-distance one planned by us.  In fact, it's mostly planned by Winnie because most of the contact and booking was handled by her.  What a shame!  <img src="http://spaces.msn.com/rte/emoticons/smile_embaressed.gif" alt="" />  I have to plan for our next trip.</p>

<p> </p>

<p>We have been to Da Jiao Wan at noon and have had a nap in the hotel after one seafood meal.  Can you bellieve that a standard double room only costs 100 RMB one night?  Again, Winnie made this bargain.  <img src="http://spaces.msn.com/rte/emoticons/smile_teeth.gif" alt="" />  You may wonder why we waste several hours on sleeping, but WHO swims at noon!  What is more, the 4 hours' bus trip makes most of us tired, but me.  <img src="http://spaces.msn.com/rte/emoticons/smile_shades.gif" alt="" /></p>

<p> </p>

<p> Anyway, we went to the seashore and planned to swim at about 4PM.  Because the typhoon "Da Wei" was approaching Yang Jiang, it's cloudy and the sea had not small wave.  Again, my dream <img src="http://spaces.msn.com/rte/emoticons/island.gif" alt="" /> that in the <img src="http://spaces.msn.com/rte/emoticons/sun.gif" alt="" />, I lay on a hammock under two coconut trees by the blue and lucid ocean, having a <img src="http://spaces.msn.com/rte/emoticons/coffee.gif" alt="" /> nearby, and some little crabs creep on the soft seashore on which colorful shells lying didn't come true.  <img src="http://spaces.msn.com/rte/emoticons/smile_confused.gif" alt="" /></p>

<p> </p>

<p> Even though that was not exactly my dreamy ocean, I was still very excited to see it and could "swim" in it.  "Swim"  is quoted here because technically I only floated with the help of the life buoy instead of swimmed. <img src="http://spaces.msn.com/rte/emoticons/smile_tongue.gif" alt="" />  On the one hand, I admit that my swiming ability is not good enough to swim in the ocean.  On the other hand, you know, the typhoon "Da Wei" was approaching and the sea had "big" waves.  At that time, I could really feel the unlimited power of the ocean.  No wonder the latest tsunami in Indian Ocean caused that kind of disaster and dilapidation.   Suddently, I feel that I am so small in this planet, in this universe.  Praying......</p>

<p>To enjoy my life!  Eager for my next wonder trip!<img src="http://spaces.msn.com/rte/emoticons/lightbulb.gif" alt="" /></p>

<p><a href="http://blufiles.storage.live.com/y1mU494rqb2Y5u6XyeVOI6DJxSm3QZ9fO2p0ghuLKULWRvTEO94fKDhlY4ekozYz17xm_urlfy7M7lQzyMsqZCqaoyR7diEicseiPhm-yTa0iNedNLPn3jwHQIM-hI0zkn2gLab9dNcXwo"><img src="http://blufiles.storage.live.com/y1mU494rqb2Y5u6XyeVOI6DJxSm3QZ9fO2p0ghuLKULWRvTEO94fKDhlY4ekozYz17xm_urlfy7M7lQzyMsqZCqaoyR7diEicseUR53a-GyS9pL85BtxdGLSgaQUqHtZep6TtufwDyFP8I" alt="" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
