<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Tag: Productivity | Thinking in Crowd / 鹄思乱想]]></title>
  <link href="http://kenspirit.github.io/tags/productivity/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kenspirit.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-06-08T22:15:53+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://kenspirit.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[鹄思乱想]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[UED in my pet project - Take Time (Part 1)]]></title>
    <link href="http://kenspirit.github.io/blog/2012/12/25/ued-in-my-pet-project-take-time-part-1/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-25T21:41:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://kenspirit.github.io/blog/2012/12/25/ued-in-my-pet-project-take-time-part-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>What is it and why I want to work on that</h2>

<p>I hope the name is brief and clear on what it should be although I was worrying whether it brings an illusion that it's telling you to <em>"Take your time.  Slow down."</em>.  Actually, it's where to take the time seriously and you can keep track of your time.</p>

<p>Why would I want to do such a seemingly boring thing?  There are three reasons:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>For those who really cares about their time, they really want to find some effective way to make their time used effectively.</p></li>
<li><p>I have been working in two software companies which both require staffs to input TIMESHEET!  Yes, we all know it's bullshit, meaningless and most of the figures are made up, but it's just required.</p>

<p>  I can understand that part of the objective is good, just like what this pet project is made for. However, mostly it's just some policy or resource monitoring required by boss.</p></li>
<li><p>Practice my development skills with some of my favorite tools by doing real work.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>Hence, I am trying to make an easy-to-use application for those who want an effective time management.  The design is basically following my <a href="http://www.thinkingincrowd.me/blog/2012/12/24/my-practices-on-time-management/">practices</a> of it and the principle of simplicity.</p>

<h2>What does it look like</h2>

<p>It should be simple in general.</p>

<ul>
<li>It's a GTD-style task web application.</li>
<li>It can plan, track and retrospect the tasks.</li>
</ul>


<h2>How to capture the time</h2>

<p>No matter you are planning tasks or actually tracking the tasks done.  You need to capture it.  There are many elements need to write down:</p>

<ul>
<li>For planning tasks: Task content, Start/End date and Estimated how long it needs.</li>
<li>For tracking tasks: Task content, Start/End date, Start/End time and how long it takes.</li>
</ul>


<p>The elements in tracking tasks covers all we need for planning tasks, hence the capturing UI should be able to unified.  Below is the draft UI designed:<br/>
<img src="https://dl.dropbox.com/u/17182499/blog/2012/12/task_capture.png" alt="Capture UI" /></p>

<ul>
<li>By default, there is a task content textbox.</li>
<li>After you input something, some additional text and input boxes are shown.</li>
</ul>


<p>You should probably be able to guess how to use it already (if not, let me know how to make it happen):</p>

<ul>
<li>If you input the task name and press "<em>Enter</em>", you start your task immediately.</li>
<li>If you input the task name and the duration it takes and press "<em>Enter</em>", you are tracking a task just finished.  It's calculated based on the current time and the duration you input.</li>
<li>If you also fills a specific date in "<em>yyyy-MM-dd</em>", you are planning tasks if it's a future date; you are tracking tasks if it's a historical date.  The last "<em>hh:mm</em>" field is optional for the task start time.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Why design like this</h2>

<p><em>4</em> fields with some easy to explain text made it can be read as a sentence.  It should be natural to fill in what is required.  And when you press "Enter" at any field, it will do different things automatically.  It should be simple enough but satisfy all the requirement.</p>

<p>I have been thinking how to capture the duration.</p>

<ul>
<li>Two fields separately for hours and mins (This app is not designed for those crazy people who need to capture seconds).</li>
<li>One field for all.</li>
</ul>


<p>Approach <em>#1</em> looks natural but needs an extra field and more key-stroke.  By taking <em>#3</em>, decimal number need to be used to express minutes.  You may question me that calculating decimal is even harder.  But think it this way:  <em>.25</em> is <em>15</em> mins; <em>.5</em> is <em>30</em> mins; <em>.75</em> is <em>45</em> mins; <em>.1</em> is around <em>5</em> mins.</p>

<p>I think it's not that difficult to use decimal to express it.  What is more, when you are actually tracking your task this way, you are guessing or trying to remember how long it took.  Your mental power is "calculating" somehow to get a number.  If it's one field, you just need to do one calculation and input.  If it's two fields, you might possibly calculating two fields, especially when your task start time is say from <em>2:35</em> to <em>4:08</em>.  I think it just doesn't matter if there is minor inaccurate.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My practices on Time Management]]></title>
    <link href="http://kenspirit.github.io/blog/2012/12/24/my-practices-on-time-management/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-24T06:22:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://kenspirit.github.io/blog/2012/12/24/my-practices-on-time-management</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>The 101</h2>

<blockquote><p>Time Management is the act or process of planning and exercising conscious control over the amount of time spent on specific activities, especially to increase effectiveness, efficiency or productivity.</p></blockquote>

<p>Everyone who cares about their time should be familiar with this concept and knows its goal - to increase effectiveness.  The <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Time_management">Wiki</a> site covers different aspects of it.</p>

<p>Here I would like to share my understandings and what my choices are to make good use of my time.<br/>
1. Planning &amp; Prioritizing<br/>
2. Protecting thy time<br/>
3. Identifying waste</p>

<h2>Planning &amp; Prioritizing</h2>

<p>Planning &amp; Prioritizing is a must.  It helps us not losing any task we have to do but also makes sure we do the most urgent &amp; important ones first.  <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Getting_Things_Done">Getting Things Done</a> is a great methodology.  However, <strong>DON'T SPEND TOO MUCH TIME ON THE LIST.</strong>  You cannot prioritize or categorize your tasks if the list fills with tons of items especially if you have some level of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Obsessive%E2%80%93compulsive_disorder">Obsessive-compulsive disorder</a>.</p>

<p>I have the same issue stated in <a href="http://simpleprogrammer.com/2012/10/28/my-15-minute-rule-to-productivity/">My 15 Minute Rule to Productivity</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>I’ll delay doing something that I know is important until the last moment that it needs to be done.</p></blockquote>

<p>Hence, my rule on making a list is: <strong>Make a task list only for the tasks I need to do TODAY and come up an estimated time on how long to take it.</strong>  How if I have something important to do in the future? Put it to calendar/reminder and also include an estimated time so that this task will go into my future TODAY task list.</p>

<p>And then the rule of picking the task from a list is: <strong>Scan the tasks and their estimated time; Pick the one I MUST start it.</strong>  This action is to take out the most IMPORTANT and URGENT task which is actually prioritizing.  The estimated time made in the first step helps me know when it is the right time to pick which task.</p>

<h2>Protecting thy time</h2>

<p>What does this mean?  It means avoid distraction.  Distraction is the major time killer which makes us ineffective.  <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pomodoro_Technique">Pomodoro Technique</a> is the one I like.  It imposes an external mechanism (a timer here) to keep us focus on work for a short period (generally 25 mins) and also have some rest inbetween.  The rest in between the working period can be used to reply your email, IM or actually relaxing your mind.  Its working style is like marathon which needs constant pacing.</p>

<p>However, this mechanism might have an issue to some knowledge worker.  Here is the view in one of <a href="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/articles/fog0000000068.html">Joel Spolsky' article</a> with which I totally agree:</p>

<blockquote><p>We all know that knowledge workers work best by getting into "flow", also known as being "in the zone", where they are fully concentrated on their work and fully tuned out of their environment. They lose track of time and produce great stuff through absolute concentration.<br/>
...<br/>
The trouble is, getting into "the zone" is not easy. When you try to measure it, it looks like it takes an average of 15 minutes to start working at maximum productivity.  Sometimes, if you're tired or have already done a lot of creative work that day, you just can't get into the zone and you spend the rest of your work day fiddling around, reading the web, playing Tetris.</p></blockquote>

<p>Hence, the Pomodoro Technique might knock you out of the zone and you should choose your own timer based on the average time you can maintain your flow state instead of 25 minutes.  Or you can just let your flow flows until you think you need to get a break.  The point is to try to maintain some continuous period to get uninterrupted.</p>

<p>But generally, Pomodoro is helpful under certain circumstances like management level people who don't even have continous time more than 25 minutes or some working environment has interruption often or someone whose productive time shorter than 25 minutes and want to extend their flow state.</p>

<h2>Identifying waste</h2>

<p>Planning is the starting process of time management, while identifying the waste is the retrospect process.  Sometimes, it's even more important than the planning.  That is because planning is working on something uncertain, while retrospect is based on reality and intended to make improvement.  History and fact can tells us more on the our regular time usage pattern.</p>

<p>How to identify waste?  Track the time and see where your time spends.  Our memory is unreliable to keep track of how long we spend on the things done.  We need to actually write it down and write it down when it happens (at the beginning or the end of the task).</p>

<p>By tracking where the time we spend, we can find out where the waste is and try to eliminate it.  Also we can consolidate those discretionary time slots to a continuous unit for more effective usage.  There is a wonderful chapter "Know Thy Time" in <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Effective-Executive-Drucker-Series-Peter/dp/0750643900/ref=sr_1_2?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1356302486&amp;sr=8-2&amp;keywords=The+Effective+Executive">The Effective Executive</a> by <em>Peter F. Drucker</em> describing how to make good use of time.  Highly recommend.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
