<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Tag: bind | Thinking in Crowd / 鹄思乱想]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.thinkingincrowd.me/tags/bind/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.thinkingincrowd.me/"/>
  <updated>2013-11-16T15:35:42+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.thinkingincrowd.me/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[鹄思乱想]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Function definition, this and bind in JavaScript]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.thinkingincrowd.me/blog/2013/06/14/function-definition-this-and-bind-in-javascript/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-14T20:00:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.thinkingincrowd.me/blog/2013/06/14/function-definition-this-and-bind-in-javascript</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I thought I know the Function definition, execution context and the behavior of <em>this</em> in JavaScript.  However, I realized that actually I don&rsquo;t or the knowlege is still not firmly grounded in my mind when I wrote some code similar to below snippet but have no instinct of the error.</p>

<p>```javascript
var TestObj = {</p>

<pre><code>a: function() {
    console.log('A');
},
b: function() {
    console.log('B');
    this.a();
}
</code></pre>

<p>};</p>

<p>TestObj.b();</p>

<p>var c = TestObj.b;
c();
```</p>

<p>The result will be as below, right?</p>

<p><code>javascript
B
A
B
A
</code></p>

<p>You might suspiciously answer No but If your instint doesnot tell you that and why, then you don&rsquo;t know JavasScript well either like me.  The result actually is:</p>

<p><code>javascript
B
A
B
TypeError: Object [object global] has no method 'a'
</code></p>

<p>It is a little bit awkward or counterintuitive at first glance but it&rsquo;s JavaScript.  It&rsquo;s the feature and amazing part.  Let&rsquo;s break it down piece by piece and see why.</p>

<h2>Function definition</h2>

<p>The <em>TestObj</em> includes two methods.  The Function definition there actually creates two anonymous functions and then the references to the functions are assigned to the properties <em>a</em> and <em>b</em>.  Those two functions are not owned by <em>TestObj</em> and just referred by the two properties of <em>TestObj</em>.  This is the most important part causes the confusion.  Hence, above code has not much difference than below except now we assign a name <em>B</em> for one of the function:</p>

<p>```javascript
function B() {</p>

<pre><code>console.log('B');
this.a();
</code></pre>

<p>};</p>

<p>var TestObj = {</p>

<pre><code>a: function() {
    console.log('A');
},
b: B
</code></pre>

<p>};
```</p>

<h2>this</h2>

<p>In <a href="http://www.ecma-international.org/publications/standards/Ecma-262.htm">ECMA-262</a> edition 5.1:</p>

<blockquote><p><strong>10.4.3 Entering Function Code</strong><br/>
The following steps are performed when control enters the execution context for function code contained in
function object F, a caller provided thisArg, and a caller provided argumentsList:</p>

<ol>
<li>If the function code is strict code, set the ThisBinding to thisArg.</li>
<li>Else if thisArg is null or undefined, set the ThisBinding to the global object.</li>
<li>Else if Type(thisArg) is not Object, set the ThisBinding to ToObject(thisArg).</li>
<li>Else set the ThisBinding to thisArg.<br/>
&hellip;</li>
</ol>
</blockquote>

<p><em>this</em> is a special keyword refers to the binding object in the current execution context of the Function.</p>

<p>Once we invoke the Function through Object method, the <em>this</em> inside the Function body actually has been set to the <em>TestObj</em> instance.  Hence, <em>TestObj.b()</em> logs B and A consecutively because <em>this.a</em> exists as a property of <em>TestObj</em>.</p>

<p>However, below statements mean differently.</p>

<p><code>javascript
var c = TestObj.b;
c();
</code></p>

<p>Actually, variable <em>c</em>  is just another reference pointing to Function B.  Hence <em>c()</em> is same as <em>B()</em>.  When directly invoking Function B, the <em>this</em> is bound to global object.  Because there is no <em>a</em> defined in the global object, error occurs.</p>

<h2>How to set a particular object as <em>this</em> to function</h2>

<p>It&rsquo;s commonly known that <em>call</em> and <em>apply</em> method can be called on the Function object providing a specific object as <em>this</em>, say:</p>

<p><code>javascript
var c = TestObj.b;
c.call(TestObj);
</code></p>

<p>The result is desirable.  However, this approach invokes the Function immediately.  This is normally not the case that a Function has to be assigned to a Reference and passed around which is meant to be executed dynamically, like:</p>

<p>```javascript
function dynamic(fn) {
  fn();
}</p>

<p>dynamic(TestObj.b);
```</p>

<p>In this case, we should not use <em>fn.call(TestObj)</em> or <em>fn.apply(TestObj)</em> because it&rsquo;s a generic Function which should have no knowledge on the Function passed in.  Hence, above is not working.</p>

<p>There is still another lifesaver though.  The <em>bind</em> method of Function.  This method can take the passed in Object like what <em>call</em> or <em>apply</em> does, but it returns a new Function whose <em>this</em> binding is set to the Object passed in.  So, above code can be revised as:</p>

<p>```javascript
function dynamic(fn) {
  fn();
}</p>

<p>dynamic(TestObj.b.bind(TestObj));
```</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s fun, isn&rsquo;t it?</p>

<p>[Edited on 2013/06/17]: Today, I saw another case which maybe confusing too.</p>

<p>```javascript
var length = 3;</p>

<p>function logLength() {
  console.log(this.length);
}</p>

<p>var TestObj = {</p>

<pre><code>length: 2,
b: logLength,
c: function() {
    (function(fn) {
        arguments[0]();
    })(logLength);
}
</code></pre>

<p>};</p>

<p>TestObj.b();
TestObj.c();
```</p>

<p>What do you think the console should log?  Will it be <em>2</em> and <em>3</em>?  Actually, the result is <em>2</em> and <em>1</em>.  Because the <em>TestObj.c()</em> actually is calling the function <em>logLength</em> on the arguments Object, and then the <em>this.length</em> is referring to its own length, which is <em>1</em>.</p>

<p>More fun, right?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
